Archives of Irish America Irish Republicanism Collection AIA.022
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Irish Republicanism Collection
1937-2003
1970-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.022
4.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box, and 4 oversize folders
The collection documents Irish American support of civil rights and Republican activities in Northern Ireland, including anti-British demonstrations in the United States and activities in support of Irish Republicans subject to deportation proceedings in the United States. Materials relating to Hunger Strikes and political prisoners in Ireland and the United States are also included.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains printed material from various Irish American organizations, including fliers, announcements, newsletters, brochures, newspaper clippings, reports, and pamphlets, relating to Irish American support of civil rights and Republican activities in Northern Ireland. Files on anti-British demonstrations in the United States and activities in support of Irish Republicans subject to deportation proceedings in the United States are found in the collection. Documentation, including a memorial publication, on the 1981 Hunger Strikes can also be found in the collection.
Of interest are files containing letters from Irish prisoners as well as fliers and pamphlets about specific individuals and activities in support of Republican activists. Two organizations of note are the American Irish Unity Committee and the Irish American Unity Conference. Two periodicals are included in the collection: Irish Republican News Service and Common Appeal. The latter consists of photocopies of newspaper stories and is described as "a periodical publication designed to inform the friends of Ireland as fully and expeditiously as possible of Irish news and matters" and goes on to note that the editorial viewpoint should be clear from the choice of articles selected for inclusion. The Irish Republican News Service files are photocopies and/or faxes of originals. Several posters depicting Hunger Strikers are found with other oversize material.
Accruals Note
Further accruals are expected.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 2 series, both arranged chronologically. I. Subject Files, 1937-1995; II. Publications, 1972-1982.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Harrison Papers AIA 009
Irish Immigration Reform Movement AIA 016
Cormac O'Malley Papers AIA 019
Patrick Daughton Collection AIA 055
Historical Note
The materials in this collection were collected and assembled by the staff of the Archives of Irish America and various donors in an attempt to document the variety of materials produced by and for the Irish American community in support of and reaction to Republican activities in the United States, the Republic of Ireland, and Northern Ireland.
Custodial History Note
The materials in this collection were collected and assembled by the staff of the Archives of Irish America and various donors. Common Appeal and Irish Republican Information Service materials were acquired with the Cormac O'Malley Papers collection (AIA 019). Other items came from the George Harrison Papers (AIA 009) and the Vertical File collection (AIA 013).
Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; Hunger strikes -- Northern Ireland.; Fliers (printed matter); Pamphlets.; Human rights |z Ireland.; Human rights.; Prisoners' writings, Irish.; Political prisoners -- Ireland.; McAliskey, Bernadette Devlin, 1947-; Irish American Unity Conference; American Irish Unity Committee; Sinn Fein; Mackin, Sean; McAliskey, Roisin.; Doherty, Joseph Patrick, 1955-; Gralton, Jimmy, 1886-1945; Quinn, Bill; Irish Northern Aid; Irish Republican Information Service; Diana, Princess of Wales, 1961-1997.; Adams, Gerry, 1948-; Irish Republican Army
- I. Subject Files, 1937-2000; 243367
  - Adams, Gerry, 1983-1995; 236405 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Support Irish Political Prisoners, Sep 1980; 301896 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - American Aid to Ulster (Phildelphia), undated; 236406 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Committee for Ulster Justice, 1971-1979; 236407 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Irish Ad Hoc Committee, 1983; 236408 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Irish Congress, 1986-1993; 236409 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Irish Unity Committee, 1981-1986; 236410 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Irish Unity Committee: Queens Division, 1981-1982; 236411 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Irish Unity Committee: Symposium July 22, 1981; 236412 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Protestants for Truth about Ireland, 1988; 236413 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Amnesty International Reports on Northern Ireland, 1978-1994; 236414 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles on Northern Ireland: Time; St. Anthony Messenger, 1981-1982; 366237 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Articles on Northern Ireland: Life / The New York Times Magazine, 1981; 366241 (Box AIAOS001, Folder 1)
  - Associated Irish Societies of New York, 1979-1980, 1986; 236415 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Barr, Jim, 1985; 236416 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Birmingham Six Committee Newsletter, Dec 1990; 236417 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Black and the Green, 1983, 1989; 236418 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Boston Three, circa 1990; 236419 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Boycott British Goods Committee, 1981-1982, undated; 236420 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Children, 1978-2000; 236421 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: General / Peace Efforts, 1937-1988; 236422 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Connolly Association (includes isues of Irish Democrat), 1993-1995; 236424 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Devenny, Ann: Deportation Case, 1984; 236425 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Doherty, Joseph, 1989-1994; 236426 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Doherty, Joseph, National Committee for, 1988-1990; 236427 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Doirse Dochais (Doors of Hope), 1988-1994; 236428 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Eire Nua, 1973, 1991-1994; 236429 (Box 1, Folder 25, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Extradition/Deportation, 1985-1996; 236430 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fliers and Pamphlets, 1980-1996; 236431 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fort Worth Five, 1973-1987; 286361 (Box 1, Folder 27A)
  - Francis Gildernew Defense Fund, 1992; 236433 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Free Nicky Kelly Coalition, 1983; 236434 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom, 1991-1995; 285305 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Good Friday Peace Agreement and Follow-up, 1998-1999; 236435 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gralton, James, undated; 236436 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gunrunning: United States to Ireland, Clippings, 1984; 236437 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - H-Block/Long Kesh, 1980; 236438 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Harrison-Falvey Defense Committee, 1982; 236439 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Human Rights/Civil Liberties/Civil Rights, 1973-1994; 236476 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Human Rights in Northern Ireland: Report to the Association of Bar of the City of New York, 1987; 236477 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hunger Strikes / Remembrances, 1981-2001; 236478 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "The IRA and Sinn Fein" Frontline; "Ireland Film, MacNeil/Lehrer Report: Transcripts, 1980, 1997; 236432 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Irish American Defense Fund, 1984-1986; 236479 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Irish American Defense Fund: "Britain's War Machine in Ireland" by Maurice Burke, 1985; 236480 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Irish American Information Service, 1997; 236481 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Irish American Labor Coalition, 1988-1990; 236482 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Irish American Student Coalition, 1986; 236483 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Irish American Unity Conference, 1983-1989; 236484 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Irish American Unity Conference, 1990-1993; 236485 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Irish American Unity Conference, 1994-1998; 236486 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Irish American Unity Conference: Newsletter, 1984, 1989, 1992-1994; 236487 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Irish American Unity Conference: Newsletter, 1996-1999; 236488 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Irish American Unity Conference: New Jersey Region, 1990-1992; 236489 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Irish Government: Statements; Address to United Nations, 1971, 1983; 236490 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Irish National Caucus, 1974-1999; 236491 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Irish National Caucus: Testimonial Dinner, 1983; 236492 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Irish National Caucus: Testimonial Dinner, 1985; 366269 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Irish National Congress, 1992, undated; 236493 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Irish Northern Aid, 1980-1996; 236494 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Irish Northern Aid: Pamphlet - A Decade of Deceit: A Detailed Look at The New York Times and The War in Ireland. INA: Irish Prisoners of War Committee (New York), 1981; 236495 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Irish Northern Aid: Regional Chapters, 1982-1993; 236496 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Irish Northern Aid: Testimonial Dinner Programs, 1978-1979; 236497 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Irish Northern Aid: Testimonial Dinner Program, 1982; 366310 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Irish Northern Aid: Testimonial Dinner Program, 1989; 366311 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Irish Republican Activities: United States and Canada, 1982-1987; 236498 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Irish Solidarity Day, 1984-1989; 236500 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Justice for Sean Mackin Committee, 1989-1991; 236505 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Legal/Political Groups, 1959-1985; 236501 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letrim Republican Monuments, 1991, undated; 236502 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Linen Hall Library, Belfast: Northern Ireland Political Collection, 1998; 236503 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - MacBride Principles, 1984-1996; 236504 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - McAliskey, Bernadette Devlin, 1982-1996; 236506 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - McAliskey, Roslin, 1997-1998; 236507 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - John McCormack Institute of Public Affairs, University of Massachusetts, Boston: "Religion and Conflict: The Case of Northern Ireland" by Padraig O'Malley, 1991, 1995; 236508 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - McCrees, Raymond: Memorial Fund, 1991; 236509 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - McGeough, Gerry: Gerry McGeough Defense Fund, 1992; 236510 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - McNamee, Eoin: Memorial Service, 1986; 236511 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Memorials and Funeral Notices: Irish Republican Activitists, 1982-1991; 236512 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom, 1971-1975; 236513 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ, New York City: Information Bulletins on Northern Ireland, 1975-1978; 236514 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New York City and State Legislative Action, 1985-1986; 236515 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - New York City Office of the Comptroller, 1986-1994; 236516 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New York City Office of the Comptroller: Report on Northern Ireland Investment, 1985; 236517 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New York Irish Political Prisoners Amnesty Coalition, 1995-1996; 236518 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Northern Ireland News Service, 1989; 236519 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Political Education Committee: American Ireland Education Foundation Inc., 1984-1992; 236520 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Princess of Wales Dinner Protest, New York City, Feb 2, 1989; 236521 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Prisoners: Cabhair (Irish Republican Prisoners Dependents Fund), 1998; 236522 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Prisoners: Cabhair (Irish Republican Prisoners Dependents Fund): Testimonial Dinner Programs, 1988-1990; 366337 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Prisoners: Cabhair (Irish Republican Prisoners Dependents Fund) Testimonial Dinner Programs, 1998-2000, 2003; 297596 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Prisoners / Defendents in United States and Ireland, 1981-1989; 236523 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Prisoners: Letters; Statements, 1983-1996; 236524 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Prisoners: Women, 1983; 236525 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bill Quinn Defense Committee, 1985-1988; 236526 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Republican Links with Black Civil Rights, 1981-1998; 236527 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Republican Movement, 1980; 285723 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Saoraoh: Ireland Solidarity Committee, undated; 236528 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Saoirse na h'Eireann, 1985-1995; 236529 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Shanley, Michael, 1988; 236530 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sinn Fein, 1980-1994; 236531 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Strip Searches, 1987, undated; 236532 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Tucson Six Defense Fund, 1993; 236533 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - White House Conference for Trade and Investment in Northern Ireland: "Northern Ireland: The Magnified Mirror," by Tom Hayden, May 1995; 236534 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - United Ireland Coalition (Washington, DC and Baltimore), 1982; 236535 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - United States Politicians: Correspondence, Documents, 1975-1990; 236536 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - U.S. v. Bernard McKeown, 1984; 236537 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - U.S. v. Brian Fleming and Charles Malone, 1990; 236538 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - U.S. v. Megahy, Duggan, Meehan and Meeker, 1982-1983; 236539 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Women's Groups, 1986, undated; 236540 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- II. Publications and Ephemera, 1972-1997; 243368
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, Jul 1972-Sep 1972; 239264 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, Oct 1972-Dec 1972; 239263 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, 1973; 239265 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, 1974; 239266 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, 1975; 239267 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Common Appeal - An T'ean, 1976, Jan 1977-Apr 1977; 239268 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Control Zone, 1985; 590448 (Box AIAOS001, Folder 4)
  - Irish Nation, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2, Oct 1984-Nov 1984; 283929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - IRIS Quarterly, Vol 1, No. 2, Nov 1981; 283931 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - IRIS: The Republican Magazine, No. 5, 7, 1983; 283930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Nov 29 - Dec 20, 1975; 239249 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Jan 1976 - Feb 1976; 239250 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Mar 1976-Apr 1976; 239251 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, May 1976-Jul 1976; 239252 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Aug 1976-Oct 1976; 239253 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Nov 1976-Dec 1976; 239258 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Jan 1977-Mar 1977; 239259 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Apr 1977-Jul 1977; 239260 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, Aug 1977-Sep 1977; 239262 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Irish Republican Information Service, 1995-1997; 236499 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Calendar: Hunger Strike 1982 [Commemoration] (2 copies), 284717 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Posters: Irish Northern Aid - Hunger Strikers, Prisoners, circa 1980s; 366394 (Box AIAOS001, Folder 3)
  - Posters: Irish Republicanism - General, undated; 591033 (Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Republican Diary. Sinn Fein Publicity Department. Dublin., 1984; 290721 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Ulster Unionist Yearbook, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Year of the Irish Hunger Strike: An American Tribute. Published by Irish Northern Aid Committee of New York, circa 1982; 239313 (Box AIAOS001, Folder 2)
    Provenance
    From Accession 2003-0004 Gina Tlamsa